one will be the one to tell their story
using their own words however they want
to tell and the other is invited to
listen carefully and really hear what
the perspective of the one who's
speaking is and then it flips the other
person will get their uninterrupted time
and the other will listen
and what's beautiful about uninterrupted
time
is that i can see
either in nonverbals or people sometimes
actually say
i've never heard that before i never
knew you felt that way
they are surprised by some of the things
that they hear during
reality
[Music]
ladies and gentlemen hello i hope you're
well i have julie here with me today um
julie you want to go ahead and give me
let's start out with kind of a bio so
kind of how you got to to to what it is
that you do and then maybe give us a low
down on what it is that you do
okay awesome well first i'll just say
thank you for having me here today jacob
i appreciate it and hi to all the
listeners um
i
currently run my business which is peer
performance solutions and we help
organizations and individuals to lift
performance and so um through that i use
consulting coaching training and even at
times mediating skills that i've amassed
through various mechanisms i've um
you know i have a couple of degrees a ba
in communication and then ma in
organizational leadership but i also am
a certified coach a certified executive
coach and a certified emotional
intelligence coach as well as a
qualified neutral in the state where i
live which is minnesota which is a
trained and certified mediator so those
are the the skills that i use in working
with
organizations teams
boards and um i really find it or even
individuals i really find it very
helpful and um wonderful work because um
the impact with people is amazing to
watch so prior to starting my business
back in 2014 full-time i worked in a
number of
consulting and research firms previously
where i was leading teams delivering
services to
global and smaller clients
and then my last full-time gig right
before i started my business was leading
a team at the university of minnesota
foundation where
the team that i led was supporting from
the operational side the major gift
effort around the university so helping
all the frontline fundraisers
with
research lists predictive modeling
things like that so
i've kind of come through a varied
career
coming to where i am the last two gigs
that i had full time i was hired
specifically to turn teams around a
little bit um improve the interface with
the group
uh
improve some team dynamics some cultural
elements and uh
i was successful in those um thanks to
the good work that the people around me
did i just set the stage if you will and
then let them shine but uh
i found that i really like doing that so
when i work with clients i work with
clients who are struggling in some way
whether it's
you know an interface issue a client
service issue
or even how to motivate a team how to
keep them performing well so i enjoy
that kind of fixer role if you will
right yeah geez yeah you have a lot of
great experience in that too so what is
the what does the actual boots on the
ground typically look like for you when
you're when you're actually face to face
with these people with these
organizations what are the conversations
that come up um what are the the common
ailments that that you seem to see
throughout
well sometimes i'm just doing helping
with planning so facilitating planning
sessions or retreats uh
figuring out where they want to head
strategic planning if you will
so that's kind of broad and big and fun
because you get to be creative and
innovative and all those things
other times it's helping to repair so if
uh i've been called in where a team
isn't
gelling well if you will to help them
address their team dynamics
i've been called in to help
performance whether a management team or
managers in working with their team
members but report to them uh
what i like to say because i hear it all
the time is that accountability
conversations are the most difficult
part of leadership right i mean those
times when you're asking somebody to do
something differently than they are
those are tough times and so i get
called in a lot for that kind of a thing
sometimes i'm working directly with the
person
who needs to kind of adjust sometimes
i'm working with the manager to help
them work with that person differently
so you know helping them to build those
skills so it can be both of those
so are people typically
you know if they're in these situations
where they're calling you in or asking
for your guidance and assistance are
they pretty
um are they reluctant to listen to what
you have to say at first or is there is
there common difficulties because i
imagine i mean you mentioned emotional
intelligence um and i think
a lot of this area and a lot of kind of
like being aware of our own actions and
how our own over overreactions our own
emotions get the best of us sometimes
that's kind of difficult to look at
within ourselves you know so i imagine
you coming in saying hey here's what we
need to be doing and here's how maybe
you're not helping or you know should
prepare don't say it like that but um
so yeah so what comes up in that in that
area
so sometimes i am called in to
work directly with the person who is
having some kind of performance issue
and um i usually am coming in as a coach
in that case so
to differentiate and kind of explain how
i think of these and
often in the industry they're thought of
this way consulting is providing advice
and coaching is really helping the
person surface their own knowledge their
own plans their own goals their own
action steps to reach those goals and
that kind of thing so i come in with a
consulting mindset even if i'm hired to
repair something so
i'm asking a lot of questions
and
yes sometimes if i've been hired because
you know executive says this leader
needs to change the way they're working
this leader may not be super welcoming
at first but because i'm going in with a
discovery mindset where i'm asking
questions i'm asking their perspective
of the situation
i'm asking them how can they work
differently within the situation to
address whatever the executive is saying
to them because it's a it's a
clear
you know the executive saying to both of
us what needs to be worked on so we're
all on the same page if that makes sense
though the the person who has to do the
work might not agree
um i asked them things like
what's gonna happen if you don't make
this change how is that going to go for
you so i'm i'm going in with a lot of
questions
and trying to help them see where it's
in their own best interest to
make a shift to think about things
differently whatever the case may be and
more often than not i've had maybe a
couple where it's kind of stalled out
but more often than not they do
kind of see that light and and
start making changes
to the degree that they are able and um
it does have positive impact i have had
a couple where
things just stalled out and and that's
you know
not great for anybody right but you know
if somebody isn't performing we're
say an executive needs them to be
that can go a direction toward maybe
they lose their job or something so it
can be hard in those circumstances but
most often the people are wanting to
keep their jobs they are wanting to be
successful and it's just helping them
figure out how
okay okay yeah that makes sense so you
kind of i like to use the term ushering
of epiphany i feel like so sometimes do
you probably present them with um like
so if you get them to say out loud okay
if you do it this way and it happens
like this what do you think will happen
or what's gonna happen if you use this
decision so having them hear themselves
say it or talk it out probably is is
very helpful to what you do i love your
phrase ushering in epiphany i love it
yeah yeah to be honest i think i stole
it from somebody else that i heard on a
podcast but it definitely sparked my
interest and i was like oh that's that's
what i like to do too in some sort of
way so
um so the word the word leadership to
you what what does leadership mean
so to me leadership doesn't isn't
specific to a role so i think of
leadership and i sometimes call it
personal leadership can be exhibited
anywhere and actually probably should be
exhibited anywhere i think that we all
exhibit leadership to some degree in our
day-to-day roles at home in the
community at work
when we put somebody into a leadership
role it heightens that to a new degree
because you have people
um reporting directly to you their
um
their way of working is gonna in some
way be inspired by you and impacted by
you so there's a heightened level if
you're put into a direct reporting kind
of role but i think we all have the
opportunity to show leadership and i
think leadership is really just for me
it's it needs to have an inspirational
motivational element but it also has to
be for good so um i i like to think of
positive impact not harming so to me
those are all elements that are
important in leadership
right right so so
i i would say
we all have some sort of leadership
capability within us you know it's kind
of about finding your own greatness or
your own leadership whatever roles in
your life that you're a leader so i've
been um
i had a couple kind of leadership roles
even back in high school i was like
sophomore class president that sort of
thing and then after um i was manager
and assistant manager at some some
retail stores that sort of thing
and uh i always and now that i i really
enjoy philosophy and just kind of like
studying all of this whole this whole
area and how people think differently
and i kind of observe
um and ask myself how do i think
differently um as a leader like how does
me being in these roles as a manager or
you know a supervisor whatever it is
how do i
j just in order to do my job well in my
opinion how do i think differently than
the people who are you know working
underneath me or the the employees um
and it's very interesting because when
you step into that role you kind of do
see um it does you know i
my skills are accented my skills are
kind of brought to the front when i step
into that role of okay i understand that
i see these things differently than
other people do because i'm not so
they're doing this task and they need to
be doing that task um so it's so it it's
very it's just it's interesting to me to
see where we can really snap into so do
you find um
do you find that people
if you can kind of push them towards it
or usher them in in towards it rather um
do you find people who didn't think they
were leaders before but you can kind of
spark it within them do you ever have an
experience with that absolutely i've had
people reluctant to step into a
leadership role that i was asking them
to step into
and um
i think that many leaders
even those that have been leading for a
long long time can lack confidence i
think we as individuals as humans can
often lack confidence right it's a it's
a human trait that can
rear up lots of times and places and i
think that confidence thing is hard to
to um tackle because it requires some
internal work and it requires a
supportive environment as well
um so i've had people um i'm thinking of
one like that i'll kind of
talk about um without naming names of
course very reluctant to step into a
leadership role but was
but i saw already how she was leading
without being in a leadership role and
the organization i was leading a
multi-faceted team um broad team with
different functions under it
really needed leaders over each of those
functions and i was asking her to step
in to lead one of those functions and
um
we had some very
honest and forthright conversations she
was honest with me about how she was
feeling i was honest with her about what
i was seeing in her and ultimately she
did up to step into that and she's been
fabulous um she's been promoted since i
know even though i'm no longer you know
in where she has
has her um work being done but i know
she's being successful and i'm so
gratified that i could help be that
support that helped move her into that
um you're i wanted to circle back to
something else you said too
that that idea of we're stepping into a
leadership role we might think
differently than other people and we
often do
um
i think that
some people
lifted into leadership have that ability
to sing think broadly strategically
um
visionary
while also managing the work that needs
to get done managing the people who are
doing the work i think some people are
such good individual performers or
contributors that they get lifted into
leadership and they are given the
support they need to
develop these skills that some people
innately have and so some of the work i
do is actually helping with some of that
kind of thing where an individual
contributor has been lifted and they
weren't given the tools initially and
some issues are coming up and now i'm
called in to help with that
right right yeah so they have some sort
of quality some sort of traits but um
maybe not the the strategies to
implement them you know and you help
with the strategies that's awesome um
yeah i think uh
leadership is just something that you
know in today's day and age i know our
news media makes us so crazy about
everything but um it's hard to it's hard
to
i imagine if you if we are younger
people you know like i think about like
teenagers if they're looking up who's
the leaders who do i listen to you know
we have influencers on social media and
all these sorts of things um
but you know a lot of the people in
shirts and ties have podiums the last
you know however many years they seem
less and less like leaders you know is
in um
you know you you probably
you may you may i'm not sure uh you may
cringe eve even more than i uh because
you're a mediator when you listen to the
way that a lot of our leaders speak to
one another um in the the non-we don't
solve any of our conflicts we just
exacerbate more it seems um
so so what what do you think about
do you think about kind of um what the
younger younger generation may be seeing
in our our um leaders that that we have
now and and then do you think of a way
that maybe we could shift it or make it
better or maybe even a way that our
current leaders could start to maybe act
act more like leaders of course this is
a broad
you know not every single politician or
whatever is evil but
but there can be and you know i hate to
label anybody evil no matter but i think
that you are correct that we have
some people in highly visible leadership
roles whether that's politics some of
our very large multinational
organizations
um you know even in churches or what
have you there can be leaders who are
exhibiting what i would call or what i
would say are not leadership traits so i
mentioned earlier that i think it's very
important for leadership to exhibit a
positive impact and not do harm i think
we can all think of times when we've
seen leaders do harm whether that's with
the rhetoric they use the way they're
talking whether that's with um some of
the actions that they're taking those
some of those things can be harmful and
i don't think of them as leadership like
um
additionally
i think that
we have so that's a leadership umbrella
and then you mentioned kind of the
mediator thing i think of that as a
relationship umbrella i think we have
some crises in both arenas to be honest
i think that the way we treat one
another
uh it can happen on social media it can
happen on
within our news media
it can happen within the leaders but
there are
bad ways of interacting there are bad
ways of
trying to solve conflict which is
sometimes shown as trying to power my
way over your way and that's not really
a conflict resolution the way i describe
it so
there are a lot of opportunities for us
to shift them some things
in terms of how our
youth and young adults and that kind of
thing see
those of us who are older more seasoned
shall we say um
i'm sure they're appalled at times but i
also think they've been trained at times
by some of those very people that are
doing the practices that aren't helpful
and so there can be both sides of that
right and i don't i think that we who
are more seasoned we who are in
leadership roles
have to take responsibility for what we
are putting out into the world and how
our modeling so we all we often talk
about modeling our best opportunity as a
leader is to model that which we want to
see so if we're modeling certain things
that we wouldn't want others to exhibit
we need to be doing some self-reflection
and shifting some things that we're
doing because
if
if the thing that just came out of your
mouth you would be appalled if somebody
said to you
that's probably a mismatch and you might
want to be thinking about that
yeah
yeah so do you think that
when i think of leadership i think of a
growth mindset do you think um all
leaders have have a growth mindset of
some sort
so i think
often if you're put into a leadership
role in an organization growth is part
of it
um i think that it's possible to show
leadership
which is influence and positive impact
without necessarily having growth um
you know you can lead in your family you
can lead in your church without
necessarily trying to grow those right
so i think that we can still show
leadership without necessarily
being in a space of needing to grow but
if we're in an organization growth is
often a part of it especially a profit
organization um
i think you know one of my personal
leadership philosophies is that
uh the organizations that focus only on
profit and only on how much money we
make for whatever the stakeholders are
that realize the money you know whether
that's shareholders or
you know private owners or whatever it
may be if that's the only thing we're
thinking of
i think we're missing out on our impact
on other stakeholder groups
we're missing out on how are we
impacting our employees how are we
impacting our customers or people we
serve so i think thinking broadly about
the stakeholders that we impact and
making sure that we're not
benefiting one group at the detriment of
others if that makes sense yeah
definitely certainly um yeah yeah so so
sticking on growth um mentioning in in
your book a little bit of your bio it
sounds like you've had your own growth
you've had your own trials and
tribulations just like all of us in this
human experience you know um and it led
you to your book um to find
five senses for success um so tell me a
little bit about about your growth and
then how it led to your book and then
tell us about your book
sure so it's funny because i started the
writing of the book back in 2015 and i
when i started writing i thought that
the book's ideas had started coming to
me in my early career as an adult but as
i got further into the writing process
and because i was sharing some personal
stories in the book as well and it was
causing me to do a lot more
self-reflection i realized that it
really started back in childhood so i
grew up in a somewhat dysfunctional home
um it wasn't as dysfunctional as some
homes that exist but it was definitely
dysfunctional and um
there wasn't a lot of
good relationship or good leadership
happening in that home so i wasn't
learning those skills as some people who
happen to be gifted with a home where
the people modeling behavior are
modeling good behavior um
i wasn't getting that so i wasn't
learning those skills early on so i had
what i call a late launch in life so i
quit high school
before i graduated i went back and
graduated i didn't go to college right
away i just started doing kind of some
admin type work
and then later realized okay i need to
you know think about how am i going to
do more in my career
be more successful make more money
because honestly the living paycheck to
paycheck was a little tough
and so i was
decided to go back to college graduated
with my ba when i was 31 so i was older
than typical
and then um during that time up till
then i was having a lot of difficulties
with relationships as well so i was
harming myself in some ways by the
situations i would get into
being in harmful situations in some
situation in some cases and
you know every one of those that
happened taught me something that i took
with me so i started i think of that
journey as kind of collecting learnings
along the way that later i realized came
into this book um so the five senses
um
is
a twist or an elevation of our our
typical five senses so most of us
realize the senses of see hear touch
taste and smell and i realize that some
people don't realize some senses i
understand also that they have
heightened other senses usually when
that case when that happens but
generally speaking we have the five
senses and what i did is i shifted those
into what i see as deeper and more
meaningful senses of observe
listen
feel
engage and appreciate
and why i see they're deeper and more
meaningful i think that when we
experience the world with our five
senses sometimes it's kind of passive we
may hear sounds but we aren't attending
to them sometimes we're in conversation
and we aren't attending to it
we may see something especially
peripherally
where we aren't you know noticing um we
could be in a conversation and not
notice the nonverbals of the other
person we could be in those situations
and not paying attention to our own
self what we're thinking and kind of
seeing observing ourselves listening to
ourselves
um
and so
when i think of the journey that led to
this book i think the observing started
way back in my youth where i was
observing
the parents and the family to try and
avoid trouble right i was a keen
observer of what was happening in the
house
i later learned to observe and listen
more in skills with
within my career so early in my career i
was asked to be a focus group moderator
which is highly listening oriented and i
learned that as much as it terrified me
because i wasn't somebody to want to get
up in front of a group and you know so
that was another kind of lesson along
the journey as i was going through
and then when i went for my master's
degree a little bit later i started
moving into the leadership thinking
and um
and i
oh in my 20s so the feel which is
the new sense for touch
um
i i was going through therapy because i
had a lot of stuff to unpackage from my
youth and i had times when i the
therapist would ask how does that make
you feel and i would say i don't even
know because i don't know what i feel i
don't know what a feeling i don't know
because i would shut that down before it
was like i was just meant to be
quiet
not
bothering anybody and so i had shut all
that down so i had to really go through
a time period where that i had to get in
touch with that stuff and so all these
little lessons i feel like
really helped me in the end to
build a successful career in leadership
in organizations i think i used all
those skills in the work i did with the
teams i led with the people that i
worked with as colleagues and then my
managers and other executives that might
be above me um and
and by building that success and feeling
like these skills were paramount in how
um
we get work done in how we
show up with one another almost every
goal that one needs to achieve or wants
to achieve
needs to be done with the collaboration
of at least one other person almost
every there are a few where you don't
but
most often you need to be able to work
with others and so
these skills are really really important
and as i gathered all those skills i
wanted to share them with others so
that's what the inspiration of the book
was
and just to kind of talk a little bit
about the last two senses so engage is
the new one for taste taste is a
multi-sensory sense right we can
smell the food we can maybe touch it we
feel the touch of it in our mouth
so it's multi-sensory so too is engaging
whether we're engaging with others or
with ourselves so another thing i talk
about in the book is that these senses
are used both with others and really
should be used for ourselves too
and then appreciate which is often the
hardest one to use for ourself because
we easily see our
our failures or our mistakes or our
downfalls and we can have negative
self-talk and all those things that
happen
but if we really truly learn to
appreciate ourselves that helps us show
up better in the world
and when we
take that appreciation to others i mean
sometimes we'll think the idea of
appreciation for something
but we don't take it and bring it to
somebody in some way whether that's with
words with the act of kindness with
something um and so i think of
appreciating as making it active i think
of all of them as making them more
active and engaged and
and
purposeful intentional
yeah yeah i like that the the difference
between
just the word itself and something
that's just so passive and into
something that's being that's more
active so
so instead of seeing it's observing
right
yeah so i
yeah i really i really like that um i
love how you laid that out so
um i'm a i'm a
meditator i have been for the last few
years um in something uh in the mental
health world i dealt with a lot of
disassociation
and something that really helps me is
doing these meditations um using my five
senses so you take you know all their
own individual time you take it slow but
you really concentrate on touch and you
feel you know all the spots where your
your shirt is touching your skin and
where your feet are touching the ground
um you know and you do that for all of
your senses and for me um someone who
struggles with disassociation from time
to time really helped me kind of
understand um my senses that we just
pass over we just plow through them you
know our our minds are just running our
running our thoughts and our our actions
so often that we don't really slow down
and get to what our senses are so i mean
yeah i really love how you laid that out
um i think a lot of people kind of
even if they just take that and just
contemplate their five senses a little
bit more deeply what what is the
experience of each of those five senses
and then we can kind of get a little bit
more in tune with
our emotions and feeling you know our
intuition our gut feeling that the stuff
that we all kind of miss out on in our
modern culture i agree
i love your meditation too focused on
the senses i meditate as well maybe not
every day like you do but i do it pretty
regularly and i've never thought to just
do a meditation like that i'm definitely
going to try that out because i think
that's a wonderful way to to meditate
because we don't
fully utilize our senses in the way that
we could they they just kind of are
whatever senses we realize we just kind
of become
used to them being there we aren't
conscious always about what feedback
what um
input am i receiving from the world from
these senses yeah
yeah yeah 100 um i would recommend
is she's a meditation teacher i think
she teaches it's called the ziva
meditation or the z technique her name's
emily fletcher
she has a book it was fairly short it
was pretty um uh
it was like not overly scientific like
she has a couple good studies in there
um
but it wasn't too over the edge where
it's really dense or anything it was
very very surface level she seemed like
a very sweet person
i watched her on some interviews and
read her book emily fletcher z technique
or something like that
yeah i definitely recommend it um okay
so let's let's shoot on over to the
world of
damage relationships or repairing our
relationships um so so let's expand you
know so so let's talk
co-worker relationships you know family
relationships friendships all of this
how do we how do we repair and how do we
you know communicate
more more forthright and better
yeah well i'm a big obviously because i
wrote the book i'm a big believer in
using our senses well to do that um but
i'll to to start talking about this i'll
talk a little bit about what happens in
a mediation because it's really powerful
in my mind
and i hear other mediators say the same
thing so when a mediator is called into
a conflict and it can be i've mediated
conflicts between
members between community members like
say neighbors i've mediated
situations that were in a chips child in
need of protective services situation i
have mediated
um
conflicts that were under the human
rights umbrella where an individual and
organization may not be agreeing about
whether a human rights issue had been
violated so i've i've mediated a wide
gamut of types of situations
and um
one of the tactics that mediators
facilitated mediators like myself do
is after kind of talking about the
process and how it will work they allow
each side
some what we call uninterrupted time
and i really love that concept of
uninterrupted time so you know the
parties will decide who will go first i
do not as a facilitative mediator i'm
not deciding they are deciding and
one will be the one to tell their story
using their own words however they want
to tell and the other is invited to
listen carefully and really hear what
the perspective of the one who's
speaking is and then it flips the other
person will get their uninterrupted time
and the other will listen
and what's beautiful about uninterrupted
time
is that i can see
either in non-verbals or people
sometimes actually say
i've never heard that before
i never knew you felt that way
they are surprised by some of the things
that they hear during that uninterrupted
time and by just setting this container
around them that's different than the
way they had been working together
you know in whatever capacity whether it
was work family whatever
by doing that
they they often
listen differently
and
the there's not the interruptive thing
that happens often in
conflict so i'm sure all of us i
certainly have betting conflicts where
you start kind of talking over each
other
that's not full listening and
we're instead of listening to what the
other person's saying in a conflict
often we're thinking about what's next
that we're gonna voice or how we're
gonna argue their point they're just
making and so with this uninterrupted
time idea it's the idea of really just
sitting back trying to put your ideas
aside for a bit
and just listen it's just about
listening and it's really quite magical
what can surface and then
what else we're looking for as mediators
during that time and beyond in the
discussion that goes back and forth
following
is where are the commonalities so even
when people are in conflict there are
usually some commonalities so maybe
there's a family conflict between two
parents but they're so
so
they're both really really dedicated to
the growth and
and nurturing of their children maybe
they have different ideas about it um
how to do it but the commonality is they
really want to nurture and love and help
them right so it's finding those
commonalities
a solution can be built on so
those are mediator practices but any
individual can take that those ideas
into any difficult conversation or
relational situation
when i go when i so sometimes i will
do something called conflict coaching
where i'm just working with one person
who's in a conflict but the other party
hasn't decided to do a full mediation
but even by working with one person and
asking them to show up with an idea of
discovery instead of you know let's talk
about this conflict but really an idea
of discovery and asking questions to
fully understand the other person's
perspective it starts to change the way
the relationship goes even if just one
side starts it so
anybody can take that into any difficult
situation those kinds of ideas and there
are more in the book
to
to try and shift the way relationships
are going and it's it's really quite
magical but it often does shift things
yeah yeah i bet it is i mean it's yeah
anything that you can i like the finding
the the common ground that commonality
because it shifts from um sometimes
we're unconsciously kind of trying to
win you know or our ego is really like
running the ship to protect us from the
painful emotions and so it's really is
is trying to win and prove itself right
or whatever it may be
but if we can shift out of that notice
we're having that and shift into a wii
versus the problem
um that that certainly helps that's
something that i have
um
of course you know i i have my
shortcomings for sure so it doesn't
always happen but i do try to
approach conflict or relationships with
them with one another as it's us versus
the problem there's really never a time
where i'm gonna feel good about winning
or one-upping on on someone you know i'm
not unless i'm in like a slam dunk
contest or something it's there's no
point in trying to slam dunk on it
someone i'm having a relationship with
yeah yeah um
so
uh let's see
performance optimization um operational
and performance optimization so what are
some basic strategies for optimization
in um
in our relationships with one another
let's say family as well as co-workers
just optimizing and getting better just
as a maybe a general statement towards
uh our relationships okay so when i
think of performance optimization i'm
often thinking of organizations i'll
talk about that first and then i'll try
to translate that into family and
community kinds of ideas so
with
performance optimization most often i'm
working with the leaders around
accountability practices
so
and sometimes project management type
practices so some of the leaders are
challenged with
the strategy development the putting a
plan in place to address or reach that
the strategy and
um and then the constant monitoring of
progress
and the
heightening or lifting up of risky
situations where progress isn't being
made
to the degree it should
and then helping them address
often that can be a performance issue
somebody not pulling it away that kind
of thing or maybe even a team not
pulling their weight and then how to
address that so it's kind of this
trickle-down effect so
it depends on the unique situation where
i might spend my time i will say that i
spend a fair amount of time in the how
to have those accountability
conversations
so um
when
i've me so i've been a leader and i've
had to have
accountability conversations with
individuals who weren't pulling their
weight fully and when i do that and this
is what i encourage the people i coach
as well to do
is
go in with that you heard me say the
word discovery a while ago go in that
with that sense of discovery so i have a
perception an observation that somebody
isn't pulling their weight for some
reason
what if i'm wrong
what if i don't understand the full
situation so first of all check my
understanding of the situation right
so going in asking so here i've observed
let's say it's missed deadlines i've
observed a few missed deadlines lately
can you tell me what's going on instead
of you can't miss these deadlines you
know there's different ways to approach
it
and so
i'm going in with the idea of
um
what can i do to
help
them
understand the situation from the other
person's perspective so maybe there's a
barrier that's causing them to miss
deadlines that exist somewhere else in
the organization and that's the thing
that needs to be addressed so you really
want to take the time to understand what
the situation is before you um
make the assumption that it is that
place you think it is right yeah
yeah yeah
go ahead go ahead continue so that's
kind of the performance aspect when it's
so often
and so often leaders can be visionary or
strategic but not good at
the day-to-day how do we get there right
so they might have good strategies
vision
they might even have some good goals
outlined for say divisions or
departments
but then when it comes to the day-to-day
work that has to trickle up into those
to make them successful they aren't sure
how to make that happen and they
some of the project management type of
um
practices i was mentioning are what are
important in that in those cases so
taking the time to
document who is responsible for what
timelines deadlines
status meetings to make sure progress is
being made
again lifting where there are risk
factors something's lagging and other
things depend on it so i help them learn
some of those practices when needed as
well
now when you take that into the family
or into the community i think you have
opportunity to do some of that but it's
you know like if i were to sit down and
say let's put this project plan together
with my husband on a certain thing he
may not be super open to that
so it's maybe you do it in a little
different way you have a conversation
about how you're going to move forward
on something
and you repeat it and is this what we're
agreeing to and getting that more verbal
type of thing and then maybe
planning a check-in can we check in on
this in a week or a month or whatever it
makes sense and see how we're doing and
so you can still use some of those ideas
of project management
even though it's a family situation
sometimes so my husband and i are
actually raising our first granddaughter
and
she has a neurological disorder and so
sometimes we actually do document some
things out for her to help her visually
see some things but it's not like you
can't do that sometimes there is a way
to do that that's appropriate
um so you can use those there and then
working in organizations the same kinds
of things like let's say you're
volunteering for your church or
a non-profit somewhere you can still
some use some of those organizational
practices i mentioned even in those
cases so if you're volunteering and
you're let's say you're on a board or
you're
working to help um deliver services for
a nonprofit you can say can we like get
this down on paper can we see what this
looks like when we document it you can
ask these questions and often people
will say yeah that's a great idea so you
can try to embed some of those it's kind
of showing that leadership idea without
having a leadership role always and and
trying to get them to employ some of
them
right right do you do you find yourself
having a lot of success um just
narrowing down goals like just kind of
deciphering going into these places or
with these people and maybe helping them
designate hey like where's where's the
front of your ship directed because
maybe that's the problem we're just
going wherever we want here is that
something that comes up often one of the
things that happens pretty frequently is
there will be a strategy and plan
and it seems good
but then the whim of a leader will
suddenly redirect action another way
so
whether that's an executive director a
vp
you know an owner an entrepreneur it
could be any scenario
they could say
oh we need to do this well when they say
that it's a new thing that wasn't part
of the strategy so what it does is it
takes effort away from that strategy so
those whims
need to be considered before they're you
know moved on if you will so sometimes
it's working with leaders to understand
where they're impacting their own plan
if that makes sense right yeah you can't
just suddenly pivot whenever you have a
gut feeling i think yeah you have to
implement strategies and plans so do you
see that um
i mean we kind of like are uh again
going more broadly
our
how does how do our leadership skills
because because i think about a lot of
the times when we're shooting for our
goals um especially in business a lot of
times it's going to be profit right you
know of course that's what shareholders
stockholders that's what they want
that's what capitalism does it's what
we're doing here we're making money of
course
do you do you find you have to kind of
like remind them that yes profit is a
goal but not the only goal do you do you
find um a way of
uh getting because there's there's got
to be a balance of keeping the human
aspect in in businesses you know in in
the uh finding more reasons why a
company is doing what it's doing uh
maybe maybe their purpose again towards
their goals they're shooting towards
these these um you know we're shooting a
basketball tour towards the net what
what it what is the net what's the hoop
um but yeah yeah so so do you find that
uh maybe we get a little bit jaded or a
little bit lost in between
is this for profit or what's our goal
yeah i think
i mean if you're talking about a a
corporate organization a for-profit
organization you're almost always
talking about trying to maximize profit
of course that is one of the goals
but it i would hope that it's also about
providing a meaningful product or
service that helps people in some way um
most are but you know there might be
some that aren't um
and
if i'm working with a leader where
the
focus is so much on the profit
that it is
negatively impacting
team members whether they're colleagues
or the people that report to them
um
i again approach it with that coaching
mindset of
and often i'm called in because there's
an issue because 360 degree um feedback
things happen and they're getting lots
of negative feedback and trying to and
then i might do interviews to try and
figure out why that's happening and then
this surfaces as an issue
and so i try to ask the question so i
unders and i
always recognize that there is a ton of
pressure on leaders so leaders
have especially at the executive level
have a very
high pressure job you know they have
those different stakeholder groups all
clamoring for their
needs to be met right whether it's the
shareholders whether it's the employees
the customers and what they need to do
is figure out how to balance that and so
when i start talking to this leader this
fictional leader that i need to help you
know or and i have helped some of them
um is that
how how can we we rebalance this
in a way that meets more people's needs
more stakeholders needs and i really
so often they can come up with ideas so
i'm trying to ask
enough insightful questions based on
what i hear from them
that they can find their own solution
and if they even after i'm asking all
sorts of different questions
they aren't finding it then i'll ask can
we brainstorm together is that okay
because coaching is their their session
it's their
you know they're
they're driving it but i'm the guide if
you will and um
and when we brainstorm together even if
i start with i've seen people do this or
that
just by virtue of brainstorming they
start bringing up ideas and often one of
their ideas or maybe one i brought up
will work for them and they'll start
trying to shift it now there's typically
when anybody tries to change behavior
there's typically a an attempt and a
backslide an attempt in the backslide so
there's time that goes into the
resolving of it right
but it's working through that over time
and hopefully i'm building enough trust
with that person and that's something
i'm aiming definitely to do
that they're bringing the challenges to
me that they're experiencing so that we
can talk about them um
problem solve figure out strategies to
do it differently next time whatever it
may be
um and with that trust thing in mind i
think it's really important
whenever we're working with people in
organizations and our families in our
communities
we can get so much more done if we're in
a trust state with people
and the best way to be in a trust state
is to co-create or co-develop something
together
so
um
there are institutions that have done
studies where they do functional mris on
brains of people who are in trusting
states and they see that the brains
actually end up mirroring each other so
it literally changes the way your brain
is showing up
so
when we
so some of the elements that go into
that trust stator definitely not what we
say we're gonna do
building safe spaces to talk about
whatever is needed
not
blaming not putting people down for
their ideas or thoughts or actions
and um
trying to get to that point where
ideas can be shared we can co-create
together
and it's a beautiful thing how
um
how that shifts things and so i'm
getting i'm trying to get that leader
that we're talking about to think about
those elements right yeah yeah that's so
interesting that's really cool thinking
about how our our brains mirror each
other when we're when we're in a
trusting state it's like you know with
the opposite of that fear response you
know the
the the state that our news seems to put
us in at all times nowadays it's the
opposite of that yeah uh i i was
actually listening to um uh he's a
a professor from up in canada i think
john vervicky um he has this this whole
series on uh the meaning crisis it's
fascinating um but he was talking this
morning uh about the the importance of
like the dialogues the logos um
the which is just like uh the dialect
our conversations with one another and
that's kind of how
uh you know back in the day how
our democracy and all the things that we
do and and experience today how it's
built you know
we we have these long conversations with
each other and ideas and being in those
trusting states are really what makes
makes humans so cool you know we can we
can collaborate and create things
together by
having our guard down being trusting
when you can trust that the other person
is going to you know
watch and observe their emotions and and
you know
try their best to help you solve the
problem without um emotions or
irrationality stepping in you know so so
yeah we can really
when we're in that trusting state is
really the optimal
like if you have a business if you have
a company if you have something that
you're trying to get done i mean it's
like the ultimate performance hack let's
let's learn how to
you know control our states of mind and
be in a trusting state so we can accept
each other's ideas and not put each
other down and
you know steer the ship in in one one
solid direction so um
what would you say through through your
journey i mean you you've gone through
so much you know just with writing the
book um all of your schooling all of
your mediating all of your coaching
what like if you kind of had to look
back at all of your journey glancing
back over your shoulder
what do you feel that you've really
learned about not just people but maybe
even about yourself and all of this
wow i have learned so much about myself
um
so i can say that the practices i put
into the book
were learned the hard way
yeah learned by me making a lot of
failures along the way
and um having some negative outcomes as
a result
and
uh learning how to shift the way i
showed up
um i did take advantage i'm so i don't
know the strengthsfinder paradigm gallup
strengths finder i am definitely a
learner in that and so i i soak in
information all the time it's just who i
am
and having done that through different
avenues whether formal education or not
um that has helped me a great deal
and so i would
say that you know for me and for others
look around
find the things that are different than
what you know exactly now
and try to
understand how they might fit and how
those practices could be beneficial to
you
um i had to do that a lot in order to
come to where i am today i had to
realize that what i knew at any given
point in my life it could be you know
basically
every year of my life okay what i know
now is not everything i need to know i
still have to keep
trying so i think of
hume as i think that we as humans have
this wonderful opportunity to keep
expanding our knowledge and expanding
who we are and how we show up throughout
our whole life and um i think it's
unfortunate when people might do that
early on and then kind of stop and live
out the rest of their days without that
continued
bringing in new ideas so i
i guess i would bring that up and i
would also bring up
the way i finished my book no matter
where anybody has been
and i believe this for myself too
because like i said i've made a lot of
mistakes no matter what we have done
there is always hope for a better
and improved future state and we just
have to figure out how to get there and
how to bring ourselves there and others
with us right so i always think of that
hope as well
yeah yeah i love you bringing in the
word hope with that that's that's so
great uh yeah and we really are you know
having a constant growth mindset you
know every year
becoming the new version of the
butterfly and last year was was the
caterpillar you know we're
we're such
we're such fluid creatures everything is
so fluid we're always um as much as we
want to kind of take our take our report
card down it's like here's what i've
accomplished and here's what i've done
here's what i haven't done or whatever
you know if sometimes we'll internalize
our our shortcomings by just okay here's
here's where i'm at right now um but
remembering that i could be more
tomorrow than i am today i can be more
today than i than i was yesterday you
know always always having that that
constant state of growth
is is really important it kind of kind
of seems like that's that's a little bit
of maybe what you've learned too is um
just just always be growing and always
be improving and looking for ways to
improve
those mistakes that we make because we
all make them we are human humans are
fallible
those mistakes we make are learnings
they aren't
catastrophes in most cases i suppose
there are some where it may feel like a
catastrophe um i have volunteered with
individuals who were in prison or in
jail and um
you know there might be times when that
feels like a catastrophe that they ended
up there but i can also tell you that in
working with those
individuals and i worked with teen girls
and then men in jail
um there is that sense of hope
and there is that sense of things could
get better and
um the type of work i was doing with
them was
helping them learn some of the conflict
resolution type skills and so they were
seeking to learn right so no matter what
your mistake remember you know if you're
blessed with the ability to walk
when we first started to walk we
couldn't do it right we fell on our
butts or our knees or whatever all the
time for a long time as we were trying
to figure it out so think of all those
mistakes as the times you fell in
learning to walk if that's what your
experience has been and
it's the same if you've learned to play
the piano or learn to sport or whatever
it may be
you had to
fail make mistakes practice practice
practice and so i talk about practicing
a lot too or experimenting
we have to try
in order to move forward and we're gonna
make mistakes in the trying because we
don't know everything right away right
so i made a lot of mistakes
and i've continued to try and i am still
continuing to try and i would encourage
others to find what they are passionate
about and experiment in the growth
toward that and keep going yeah keep
going that's so perfect that's what i
was going to say was just keep going
that's always the most important thing i
learned to ride a um a unicycle when i
was younger and that was this something
that clicked in my head was whenever you
feel like you're about to fall just keep
pedaling
and it was it's this dorky thing that
somehow it's just i haven't ridden a
unicycle in years and years but uh it is
something that helps just just keep
going just keep trying you know it's
never a like i said we want to take out
that report card and judge ourselves and
here's what i'm getting it's no no you
failed you did something incorrectly or
you maybe you went on the wrong path for
a little while no you're not done keep
going you're good adjust pivot um cool
hey so i just want to make sure can we
get can we send the audience to your
website where can they get your book
let's give them all the info where can
we find more more about you
sure so i have two websites one is peer
p e e r performance solutions dot com
and the other is my name julie j u l i
know e
geske g e s k e peer p e e p-e-e-r.com
no hyphen in there and um the book is
available via either of those amazon
wherever you'd like to go barnes and
noble whatever site you would like to go
awesome wonderful yeah it's on kindle as
well which is always nice um
so let's end with one more question uh i
was i was thinking of one i think that
you would have a good answer too how
about um if you if you were to you know
looking in the camera imagine you're
speaking to the the leader within every
listener like this is you're speaking to
the leader within all of us we have
something that's a leader what's what's
a message that comes to mind what's
something that we we could all hear or
maybe would help us all kind of lean
towards our leadership version of
ourselves what do we need to hear
so what immediately came to mind
is that sometimes and i can say i've
been here
sometimes we think
we can't change something sometimes we
think the situation we're in is just too
bad too difficult whether it's a toxic
work environment a toxic home life a
toxic whatever
we think it
is impossible
for us to have impact on it
but if we
look inside of ourselves and figure out
what little changes we can make if we
show up to a relationship differently if
we ask questions
if we share our ideas because i bet in
those circumstances there are a lot of
ideas floating in somebody's head i've
had that happen
um
if we are
willing to experiment with those ideas
of
the questions the sharing the
um thinking what i can do
we actually can have impact we actually
can
help things shift even when
we think it's hopeless even when we
think it's too much
um too difficult too overwhelming
um so try to find that little place
inside of you and i believe that we are
all given
you know a strength a light i call it i
think we all have a light inside of us
and find that light inside of yourself
and that light is meant to
shine positive energy on others right
and yourself
and so if you can find that internal
light and let it
give you courage
to
try and experiment and
see what shifts
i think you'd be surprised at what
what influence and impact you can have
in the end
um wow that was fantastic thank you so
much that was a great answer julie
i'm definitely going to clip that out
but okay well hey thank you so much for
your time i really appreciate it thanks
for the work that you do thanks for um
writing your book so uh again i really
appreciate your time and and i had a
great conversation today julie thanks so
much for having me on jacob it was so
great yeah yeah so um i'll be in touch
we'll post the episode probably in a few
weeks here but if we need to talk we'll
be in touch via email okay all right
sounds great thank you all right take
care listeners love yourself drink some
water stretch and uh check out julie's
book have a good rest your day thank you
junkyard love podcast
[Music]
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
you